Harlan Gallery Collection 1967-2010 (bulk 1972-1978)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harlan Gallery Collection 1967-2010, (bulk 1972-1978)
MS 512
Harlan Gallery (Tucson, Ariz.); Harlan, Roger; Harlan, Pamela
The Harlan Gallery (1972-1978), located in Tucson, Arizona, was owned by Roger and Pamela Harlan. The gallery focused on contemporary artists of the Southwest and gave them a place to showcase their art when there were few galleries in the Southwest showing anything other than "Western Art". The collection contains information about the Harlan Gallery, such as correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings. This collection also has materials pertaining to various, featured artists of the Harlan Gallery. These materials include artwork, publicity materials, correspondence, and photographic materials.
3 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
The Harlan Gallery was opened in 1972 in Tucson, Arizona by Roger and Pamela Harlan. The Harlan Gallery concentrated on contemporary artists of the Southwest that who had few venues or galleries that were showing contemporary art. Many of the artists that they showcased have gone on to make a name for themselves in the art world and in other mediums. Some examples would include Jürgen Partenheimer who became one of the foremost contemporary artists working in Germany today; Ron Shelton, a screen writer and movie director for such films as Bill Durham and White Men Can’t Jump; Karen Truax, a leading female photographer; and Luis Jiménez, a nationally acclaimed sculptor of fiberglass art pieces. These and other Tucson artists were given the opportunity to share their creativity through the Harlan Gallery. The gallery closed in 1978. Shortly after closing, Roger Harlan became the Interim Director at the Tucson Museum of Art, and later was Deputy Director of the Arizona Commission on the Arts in Phoenix. Pamela Harlan helped facilitate the gifting of the Lawrence J. Heller collection, acquired by her father, to the Tucson Museum of Art.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series.
Series I: Business Materials 1972-1984, undated
Series II: Artists and Galleries 1963-2010, undated
Series III: Artwork 1967-1990, undated
Scope and Content Note
The inclusive dates for this collection are 1967-2010, with the bulk of the material dating from 1972-1978. The Harlan Galley had close ties to the Tucson Museum of Art and the Phoenix Art Museum and so materials including correspondence, exhibition information, and publicity materials are included within the collection. Materials from noteworthy artists that the Harlan Gallery showcased can be found in this collection-including Luis Jiménez, Nancy Tokar Miller, Ron Shelton, Jim Waid, John Wenger, and Jürgen Partenheimer. Prints, negatives, and positives of artwork from these noteworthy artists and others are represented in the collection. This collection includes publicity materials including exhibition catalogs, postcards, and posters that display artwork from Tucson artists. Correspondence from these artists concerning their life and work can be found here as well. Portfolios of silkscreen prints that were created by Tucson artists and published by the Harlan Gallery, in conjunction with the Arizona Theater Company (then known as the Arizona Civic Theater), are also in this collection. Physical artwork from Nancy Tokar Miller, Luis Jiménez, Andrew Rush, Ron Shelton, Jim Waid and other Arizona artists are also present within the collection.
Access Terms
Art Museums—Arizona--Tucson
Art, American--Arizona--20th century
Art, American--Arizona--Tucson--20th century—Exhibitions
Artists--United States--20th century
Artists--United States—Correspondence
Harlan Gallery (Tucson, Ariz.)
Jimenez, Luis, 1940-2006
Miller, Nancy Tokar
Shelton, Ronald W.
Tucson Museum of Art
Wenger, John
Waid, Jim, 1942
Container List
- Series I: Business Materials, 1972-1984; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. It contains materials concerning the Harlan Gallery, including correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
  - Adhesive Recipe, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence A-Z, 1972-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Artists, 1976-1978; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Tucson Museum of Art, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs The Harlans and the Gallery, 1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publicity Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Artists and Galleries, 1963-2010; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains materials from artists and galleries that were significant to the Harlan Gallery. Materials include correspondence, financial documents, photographs of artwork, and publicity materials. Some items pertaining to these artists are oversized and can be found in Box 2.
  - James Antonie, 1976-1978; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lars Bo, 1972; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gallery Artists Miller, Shelton, Waid, Wenger, 1973-1974; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth Foster Gjelsness, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barbara Grygutis, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dorothy Hay Collection, 1972-1973; undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lawrence J. Heller Collection, 1971-1977; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lawrence J. Heller Collection Artists Biographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Luis Jiménez, 1977-2006; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jacob Landau, 1970-1993; undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Thomas Lewis, 1972; undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, 1973-1983; undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jeff Mitchell, 1974-1980; undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jürgen Partenheimer, 1973-2010; undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Phoenix Art Museum, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Edward Putzar, 1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Andrew Rush, 1963-1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fritz Scholder, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ron Shelton, 1974-2010; undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Kaki Shields, 1976-1977; undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Spectrum Gallery, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bruce and Clonard Thomas, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Karen Truax, 1976-1977; undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Tucson Museum of Art, 1972-1985; undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jim Waid, 1974-2006; undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - John Wenger, 1970-1976; undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series III: Artwork, 1967-1990; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically by artist. It is composed of artwork and posters that were created by Harlan Gallery artists. Publicity posters for the Harlan Gallery, artist exhibitions, and the Arizona Civic Theater are found here as well.
  - Daniel Berrigan and Thomas Lewis, Vietnamese Letter, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Robert Buitron, The Legend of Ixtaccihuatl y Popocatepetl (Calendar), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - James Davis, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James Davis, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harlan Gallery Publicity Ad, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - David Jones, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - David Jones, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Luis Jiménez, Ancient Roots/New Visions Exhibition Poster, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Patricia Johnson, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Patricia Johnson, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Patricia Johnson, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Yoshiko Kanai, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Yoshiko Kanai, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Thomas Lewis, Trial and Prison: A Portfolio of Ten Etchings, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Charles Littler, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Charles Littler, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Arizona Civic Theater, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Galaxy, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Nancy Tokar Miller, Untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Edward Putzar, Photographs Exhibition Poster, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Andrew Rush, Harlan Exhibition Poster, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ron Shelton, 20 Illustrations for an Unwritten Novel Exhibition Poster, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Jim Waid, Arivaca, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jim Waid, Landscapes: Real and Imagined Exhibition Poster, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Jim Waid, Publicity Poster, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)